<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Academic &#8211; Ross Churchley</title>
	<atom:link href="https://rosschurchley.com/category/academic/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://rosschurchley.com/</link>
	<description>A commonplace book by Ross Churchley</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 07:57:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.4</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://rosschurchley.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/android-chrome-512x512-1-150x150.png</url>
	<title>Academic &#8211; Ross Churchley</title>
	<link>https://rosschurchley.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A submodular measure and approximate Gomory-Hu theorem for packing odd trails</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2018/a-submodular-measure-and-approximate-gomory-hu-theorem-for-packing-odd-trails/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=297</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Although I&#8217;ve left academia, Bojan Mohar and I have published a new paper in the proceedings of SODA exploring the &#8220;perimeter&#8221; measure that plays a key role in my doctoral research. It is mostly based on Chapter 4 of my PhD thesis.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Although I&#8217;ve left academia, Bojan Mohar and I have published a new paper in the <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/3174304.3175281">proceedings of SODA</a> exploring the &#8220;perimeter&#8221; measure that plays a key role in my doctoral research. It is mostly based on Chapter 4 of my <a href="https://rosschurchley.com/2017/phd-thesis/">PhD thesis</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Odd disjoint trails and totally odd graph immersions</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2017/phd-thesis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=293</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have succesfully defended my PhD thesis! It&#8217;s &#8220;packed&#8221; with results on graph immersions with parity restrictions, and &#8220;covers&#8221; odd edge-connectivity, totally odd clique immersions, and a new submodular measure that&#8217;s intimately connected with both. I am grateful to NSERC for funding my degree with a Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship, and to my [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have succesfully defended my PhD thesis! It&#8217;s &#8220;packed&#8221; with results on graph immersions with parity restrictions, and &#8220;covers&#8221; odd edge-connectivity, totally odd clique immersions, and a new submodular measure that&#8217;s intimately connected with both.</p>



<p>I am grateful to NSERC for funding my degree with a Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship, and to my supervisor Bojan Mohar.</p>



<span id="more-293"></span>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>The odd edge-connectivity between two vertices in a graph is the maximum number λ<sub>o</sub>(<em>u</em>,<strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>v</em>) of edge-disjoint (<em>u</em>,<strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>v</em>)-trails of odd length. In this thesis, we define the perimeter of a vertex-set, a natural upper bound for the odd edge-connectivity between some of its constituent pairs. Our central result is an approximate characterization of odd edge-connectivity: λ<sub>o</sub>(<em>u</em>,<strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>v</em>) is bounded above and below by constant factors of the usual edge-connectivity λ(<em>u</em>,<strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>v</em>) and/or the minimum perimeter among vertex-sets containing <em>u</em> and <em>v</em>.</p>



<p>The relationship between odd edge-connectivity and perimeter has many implications, most notably a loose packing–covering duality for odd trails. (In contrast, odd paths do not obey any such duality.) For Eulerian graphs, we obtain a second, independent proof of the packing–covering duality with a significantly better constant factor. Both proofs can be implemented as polynomial-time approximation algorithms for λ<sub>o</sub>(<em>u</em>,<strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>v</em>). After observing that perimeter satisfies a submodular inequality, we are able to prove an analogue of the Gomory–Hu Theorem for sets of minimum perimeter and, consequently, to construct an efficient data structure for storing approximate odd edge-connectivities for all vertex pairs in a graph.</p>



<p>The last part of the thesis studies more complicated systems of odd trails. A totally odd immersion of a graph <em>H</em> in another graph <em>G</em> is a representation in which vertices in <em>H</em> correspond to vertices in <em>G</em> and edges in <em>H</em> correspond to edge-disjoint odd trails in <em>G</em>. Using our perimeter version of the Gomory–Hu Theorem, we describe the rough structure of graphs with no totally odd immersion of the complete graph <em>K<sub>t</sub></em>. Finally, we suggest a totally odd immersion variant of Hadwiger’s Conjecture and show that it is true for almost all graphs.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>You can also read two papers published based on my results:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://rosschurchley.com/2016/weak-duality-for-packing-edge-disjoint-odd-trails/">Weak duality for packing edge-disjoint odd trails</a></li>



<li><a href="https://rosschurchley.com/2018/a-submodular-measure-and-approximate-gomory-hu-theorem-for-packing-odd-trails/">A submodular measure and approximate Gomory–Hu theorem for packing odd trails</a></li>
</ul>



<p>or look at the slides I used at my defence:</p>



<div data-wp-interactive="core/file" class="wp-block-file"><object data-wp-bind--hidden="!state.hasPdfPreview"  class="wp-block-file__embed" data="https://rosschurchley.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/slides.pdf" type="application/pdf" style="width:100%;height:600px" aria-label="Embed of slides."></object><a id="wp-block-file--media-681513ce-50bf-42ea-abd1-168422ae2f17" href="https://rosschurchley.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/slides.pdf">slides</a><a href="https://rosschurchley.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/slides.pdf" class="wp-block-file__button wp-element-button" download aria-describedby="wp-block-file--media-681513ce-50bf-42ea-abd1-168422ae2f17">Download</a></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Weak duality for packing edge-disjoint odd trails</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2016/weak-duality-for-packing-edge-disjoint-odd-trails/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2016 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=289</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a new paper, coauthored with my supervisor Bojan Mohar and colleague Hehui Wu and presented at the SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms! It is my first foray into graph immersions with parity restrictions. I am grateful to NSERC for supporting this research through an Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have a <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.5555/2884435.2884580">new paper</a>, coauthored with my supervisor Bojan Mohar and colleague Hehui Wu and presented at the SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms! It is my first foray into graph immersions with parity restrictions.</p>



<p>I am grateful to NSERC for supporting this research through an Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>On the polarity and monopolarity of graphs</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2013/on-the-polarity-and-monopolarity-of-graphs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=279</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a new paper published in Graphs and Combinatorics! It&#8217;s my favourite paper to come out of my research with Jing Huang at the University of Victoria — the third written chronologically, and the last to be published. The main result is that the structure of monopolar partitions in claw-free graphs can be fully [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/jgt.21755">new paper</a> published in Graphs and Combinatorics! It&#8217;s my favourite paper to come out of my research with Jing Huang at the University of Victoria — the third written chronologically, and the last to be published. The main result is that the structure of monopolar partitions in claw-free graphs can be fully understood by looking at small subgraphs and following their direct implications on vertex pairs.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Solving partition problems with colour-bipartitions</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2012/solving-partition-problems-with-colour-bipartitions/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2012 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=273</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have a new paper with Jing Huang in Graphs and Combinatorics! This was the culmination of my undergraduate research, and shows that a single strategy can be used to solve the monopolar partition problem in all graph classes for which the problem was previously known to be tractable, including line graphs and claw-free graphs. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00373-012-1270-z">a new paper</a> with Jing Huang in Graphs and Combinatorics! This was the culmination of my undergraduate research, and shows that a single strategy can be used to solve the monopolar partition problem in all graph classes for which the problem was previously known to be tractable, including <a href="https://rosschurchley.com/2011/line-polar-graphs-characterization-and-recognition/">line graphs</a> and <a href="https://rosschurchley.com/2013/on-the-polarity-and-monopolarity-of-graphs/">claw-free graphs</a>.</p>



<p>This research was completed in the summer of 2010, my last undergraduate research term. I am grateful to NSERC for funding my work with a Undergraduate Student Research Award, and to my supervisor and coauthor Jing Huang.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>On graph-transverse matchings</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2012/msc-thesis/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2012 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=267</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I have successfully defended my master’s thesis on graph-transverse matching problems! It considers the computational complexity of deciding whether a given graph admits a matching which covers every copy of a fixed tree or cycle. The thesis is related to my previous work on cycle-transverse matchings and P4-transverse matchings and, roughly speaking, shows that H-transverse [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I have successfully defended <a href="https://hdl.handle.net/1828/4137">my master’s thesis</a> on graph-transverse matching problems! It considers the computational complexity of deciding whether a given graph admits a matching which covers every copy of a fixed tree or cycle.</p>



<p>The thesis is related to my previous work on <a href="https://rosschurchley.com/2011/complexity-of-cycle-transverse-matching-problems/">cycle-transverse matchings</a> and <a href="https://rosschurchley.com/2011/line-polar-graphs-characterization-and-recognition/"><em>P</em><sub>4</sub>-transverse matchings</a> and, roughly speaking, shows that <em>H</em>-transverse matchings are NP-hard to find when <em>H</em> is a big cycle or tree, and tractable when <em>H</em> is a triangle or a small tree.</p>



<span id="more-267"></span>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>Given graphs <em>G</em>, <em>H</em>, is it possible to find a matching which, when deleted from <em>G</em>, destroys all copies of <em>H</em>? The answer is obvious for some inputs—notably, when <em>G</em> is a large complete graph the answer is &#8220;no&#8221; — but in general this can be a very difficult question. In this thesis, we study this decision problem when <em>H</em> is a fixed tree or cycle; our aim is to identify those <em>H</em> for which it can be solved efficiently.</p>



<p>The <em>H</em>-transverse matching problem, TM(<em>H</em>) for short, asks whether an input graph admits a matching <em>M</em> such that no subgraph of <em>G</em>−<em>M</em> is isomorphic to <em>H</em>. The main goal of this thesis is the following dichotomy. When <em>H</em> is a triangle or one of a few small-diameter trees, there is a polynomial-time algorithm to find an <em>H</em>-transverse matching if one exists. However, TM(<em>H</em>) is NP-complete when <em>H</em> is any longer cycle or a tree of diameter ≥ 4. In addition, we study the restriction of these problems to structured graph classes.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>I am grateful to NSERC for funding my degree with a Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship, and to my supervisor Jing Huang.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Complexity of cycle-transverse matching problems</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2011/complexity-of-cycle-transverse-matching-problems/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=259</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Earlier this year, I presented the first results of what would become my master&#8217;s thesis at the International Workshop on Combinatorial Algorithms. The paper, coauthored with Jing Huang and Xuding Zhu, has now been published in the LNCS proceedings. It studies the computational complexity of the following problem: in a given graph, is there a [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Earlier this year, I presented the first results of what would become my master&#8217;s thesis at the International Workshop on Combinatorial Algorithms. The paper, coauthored with Jing Huang and Xuding Zhu, has now been published in the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-25011-8_11">LNCS proceedings</a>. It studies the computational complexity of the following problem: in a given graph, is there a matching which breaks all cycles of a given length?</p>



<p>I am grateful to NSERC for funding this research with a Alexander Graham Bell Canada Graduate Scholarship.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>List-monopolar partitions of claw-free graphs</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2011/list-monopolar-partitions-of-claw-free-graphs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2011 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=257</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Shortly after solving the monopolar partition problem for line graphs, Jing Huang and I realized that our solution could be used to solve the &#8220;precoloured&#8221; version of the problem, and then further extended to claw-free graphs. Jing presented our result at the French Combinatorial Conference and the proceedings have now been published in Discrete Mathematics.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Shortly after solving the monopolar partition problem for line graphs, Jing Huang and I realized that our solution could be used to solve the &#8220;precoloured&#8221; version of the problem, and then further extended to claw-free graphs. Jing presented our result at the French Combinatorial Conference and the proceedings have <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.disc.2011.08.022">now been published</a> in Discrete Mathematics.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Line-polar graphs: characterization and recognition</title>
		<link>https://rosschurchley.com/2011/line-polar-graphs-characterization-and-recognition/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2011 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Academic]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Math]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://rosschurchley.com/?p=255</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;ve published a new paper in the SIAM Journal on Discrete Mathematics! The work is the result of the research term I took as an undergraduate in the summer of 2009. It studies the edge versions of the monopolar and polar partition problems, and presents a linear-time solution to both. I am grateful to NSERC [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I&#8217;ve published <a href="https://doi.org/10.1137/100789208">a new paper</a> in the SIAM Journal on Discrete Mathematics! The work is the result of the research term I took as an undergraduate in the summer of 2009. It studies the edge versions of the monopolar and polar partition problems, and presents a linear-time solution to both.</p>



<p>I am grateful to NSERC for funding my work with a Undergraduate Student Research Award, and to my supervisor and coauthor Jing Huang.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
